<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two ordinances of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament :I. concerning the names of the committee for the associated counties of Norfolk, Suffolk, Essex, Cambridge, Hertford and Huntington, together with instructions for the said committee. II. For explanation of a former ordinance for sequestration of delinquents estates: with an oath for renouncing of poperie. Also three speciall orders; viz. I. That the divines of the assembly that are resiants of the associated counties, ... be desired to go down into their severall counties, to stirre up the people to rise for their defence. II. That the Lord Generall the Earl of Essex, be desired to grant a commission to the Earl of Manchester, to be Sergeant Major Generall of all the forces of the six associated counties. III. That the said six associated counties shall forthwith raise a bodie of ten thousand foot and dragoons to withstand the enemie. Ordered by the Commons in Parliament ... H. Elsynge, Cler, Parl. D. Com.</title>
            <title>Proceedings. 1643-08-14</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2409A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225900</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897585</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897585</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132886</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83552)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132886)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2515:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two ordinances of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament :I. concerning the names of the committee for the associated counties of Norfolk, Suffolk, Essex, Cambridge, Hertford and Huntington, together with instructions for the said committee. II. For explanation of a former ordinance for sequestration of delinquents estates: with an oath for renouncing of poperie. Also three speciall orders; viz. I. That the divines of the assembly that are resiants of the associated counties, ... be desired to go down into their severall counties, to stirre up the people to rise for their defence. II. That the Lord Generall the Earl of Essex, be desired to grant a commission to the Earl of Manchester, to be Sergeant Major Generall of all the forces of the six associated counties. III. That the said six associated counties shall forthwith raise a bodie of ten thousand foot and dragoons to withstand the enemie. Ordered by the Commons in Parliament ... H. Elsynge, Cler, Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <title>Proceedings. 1643-08-14</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Aug. 14. anno Dom. 1643</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Essex, Robert Devereux, --  Earl of, 1591-1646 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Manchester, Edward Montagu, --  Earl of, 1602-1671 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  Committee for Sequestration of Delinquents' Estates --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Military --  1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132886:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>TWO ORDINANCES of the LORDS AND COMMONS</hi> Aſſembled in <hi>PARLIAMENT:</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Concerning the Names of the Committee for the Aſſociated Counties of <hi>Norfolk, Suffolk, Eſſex, Cambridge, Hertford</hi> and <hi>Huntington,</hi> together with Instructions for the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> For Explanation of a former Ordinance for Sequeſtration of Delinquents Eſtates: with an Oath for renouncing of Poperie.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo Three ſpeciall Orders;</hi> viz.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> That the Divines of the Aſſembly that are Reſiants of the Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated Counties, and now attending the Aſſembly, be deſired to go down into their ſeverall Counties, to ſtirre up the people to riſe for their defence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> That the Lord Generall the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> be deſired to grant a Commiſſion to the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> to be Sergeant Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of all the Forces of the ſix Aſſociated Counties.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> That the ſaid ſix Aſſociated Counties ſhall forthwith raiſe a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Ten thouſand Foot and Dragoons to withſtand the Enemie.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>
                           <hi>ORdered by the Commons in Parliament, that theſe</hi> Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Inſtructions, <hi>and</hi> Orders, <hi>be forthwith printed and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>H. Elſynge, Cler, Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aug. 14.</hi> Anno Dom. <hi>1643.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <pb facs="tcp:132886:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:132886:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Die Martis 8. Auguſti, 1643.</hi> An ordinance of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, for na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a Committee for the Aſſociated Counties, of Norfolk, Suffolk, Eſſex, Cambridge, Hertford<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Huntingdon.</head>
            <p>THe Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, taking into their ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration the great danger of the Proteſtant Religion, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Popery by a Popiſh Army, and the daily Rapines, Pilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, Burnings, and ſpoylings of his Maieſties good Subjects in many parts of this Kingdome, by ſeverall Armies of Horſe and Foot raiſed, conſiſting for the moſt part of bloudy minded Papiſts, Iriſh Rebells, Atheiſts, Forreiners, and of the Prelaticall party; And eſpecially ſeeing that the Earl of <hi>Newcastle,</hi> with his whole Army, ſince the late ſurrendring of <hi>Gainsborough</hi> unto him, is march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards and ready to fall upon the Aſſociated counties of <hi>Norfolk, Suffolk, Eſſex, Cambridge, Hertford</hi> and <hi>Huntingdon:</hi> Therefore the ſaid Lords and Commons have thought it moſt neceſſary, and do hereby Ordain, Nominate, and Appoint, Sir <hi>John Hobart</hi> Knight and Baronet, Sir <hi>John Palgrave</hi> Knight and Baronet, Sir <hi>Miles Hobart,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Hoogan,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Gaudy,</hi> Sir <hi>Iſaac Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Aſhley,</hi> Knights<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Thomas Windham, John Spylman, John Cook, Gregory Goulſall, Francis Jermy, Robert Woods, Robert Wilton, William Cook, Thomas Weight, Martin Sidley, Thomas Sotherton, John Brewſter,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Ruſſell</hi> of Baſham, Eſquires, for the ſaid county of Norfolk. Sir <hi>Edmund Bacon,</hi> Sir <hi>William Spring,</hi> Knights and Baronets, Sir <hi>Thomas Barnardiſton</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>William Soam, Theophilus Vaughan, Maurice Barrow, Thomas Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Nathaniel Bacon</hi> of Friſton, <hi>Nathaniel Bacon</hi> of Ipſwich, <hi>Robert Brewſter, Francis Bacon, Edmund Harvey, Iſaac Appleton, Thomas Tirrill</hi> of Gipping, <hi>James Hobart, Gibſon Lucas, Thomas Cole</hi> of Haverill, <hi>William Bloyſe,</hi> and <hi>William Laurence,</hi> Eſquires for the ſaid county of Suffolk. Sir <hi>Thomas Honywood,</hi> Sir <hi>William Roe,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Holcroft,</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Everard,</hi> Knights, <hi>John Sayer, Arthur Barnardiſton, John Wright, Richard Harlarkinden, Edward Palmer, Timothy Middleton, Dean Tindall, William Humfreevile, John Eldred, John Eliston,</hi> of Geſthorp, <hi>Robert Galthorp, William Atwood</hi> of Wrightbridge, <hi>John Atwood</hi> of Muchſhwaltham; Eſquires, <hi>Samuel Read,</hi> Doctour of Phyſick, <hi>John Young</hi> and <hi>John Sorrell,</hi> Gent. for the ſaid county of Eſſex. Sir <hi>John Cuts,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Martin,</hi> Knights, <hi>Oliver Cromwell, Francis Ruſſell, Thomas Coke, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam March, James Tompſon, Thomas Ducket, Robert Caſtle, Robert Clerk, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Clench, Dudley Pope, Thomas Bendiſhe, John Welbore, Richard Foxton,</hi> Eſquires, and <hi>Samuel Spaulding,</hi> Gent. for the ſaid county of Cambridge. Sir <hi>John Garrat</hi> Baronet, Sir <hi>John Witterreung</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>John Read</hi> Baronet, <hi>John Hayden, Ralph Freeman, William Leaman, William Prieſtly, Gabriel Barber</hi> of Hertford, <hi>John Robotham, Henry Mewtis, Ralph Pemberton,</hi> Captain <hi>Richard Porter, Adam Waſhington, John Scrogs, Alexander Wilde, Thomas Tooke,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132886:3"/>John King,</hi> Eſquire: for the ſaid county of Hertford. Sir <hi>Miles Sands</hi> junior, Knight, <hi>John Hubart, Humberſton March,</hi> Eſquires, and <hi>Thomas Caſtle</hi> Gent. for the ſaid Iſle of Ely. <hi>John Thacker</hi> Major, <hi>Adrian Parmiter, John Tooly, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund Burnam, Matthew Peckover, Henry Wats, Matthew Lindſey, William Symonds,</hi> Aldermen of the city of Norwich, <hi>John Greenwood</hi> Sheriff of the ſame, <hi>Samuel Smith</hi> Eſquire; for the ſaid county of the city of Norwich. <hi>Onſlow Winche, Torrell Jocelyne, Oliver Cromwell, Thomas Tempter, John Caſtle, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Burwell,</hi> and <hi>Edward Mountague,</hi> Eſquires; <hi>Robert Vinter, Robert Harvey,</hi> and <hi>Garvall Fulwood,</hi> Gent. for the ſaid county of Huntington; or any ſeven or more of them, three whereof to be Deputy-Lieutenants, and the whole ſeven to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of one out of every the ſaid counties reſpectively, and one out of the city of <hi>Norwich,</hi> to be a ſtanding and conſtant Committee, who ſhall have power to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Affairs of the ſaid Aſſociated counties, according to their Inſtructions here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſpecified.</p>
            <p>And for the better effecting of the premiſes, the ſaid Committee, or any ſeven or more of them as aforeſaid, ſhall be reſident at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> or at ſome other of the Frontier Towns of the Aſſociation, or ſome other convenient place within the ſaid counties, and ſhall have power to adjourn themſelves, from time to time, and from place to place, as they ſhall think fitting. And the ſaid Lords &amp; Commons in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, do hereby nominate and command, <hi>Thomas Sotherton</hi> and <hi>Martin Sid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> Eſquires for the countie of Norfolk; <hi>Edmund Harvey</hi> and <hi>Thomas Cole,</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires for the county of Suffolk; Sir <hi>William Roe</hi> Knight, and <hi>Timothy Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Eſquires for the county of Eſſex; <hi>Thomas Ducket,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Caſtle,</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires for the county of Cambridge; <hi>Henry Mewtis</hi> and <hi>Ralph Freeman,</hi> Eſquires for the county of Hertford; <hi>Onſhow Winche</hi> and <hi>Abraham Burwell,</hi> Eſquires for the county of Huntingten; and <hi>Samuel Smith,</hi> Eſquire for the county of the city of Norwich, preſently to attend this ſervice. And after they or (or more of the ſaid Commiſſioners) ſhall have ſate fourteen dayes, then the minor half of the ſaid Committee to be free, and they to ſend for ſo many others in their ſtead, out of every the ſaid reſpective counties and city of Norwich, and the major half there ſtill to remain other fourteen dayes, and then they alſo are free; and they then to ſend for ſeven others, one out of every the ſaid counties and city of Norwich as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; and to change the Committee by half at once ſucceſſively during theſe troubles, or till further order be taken, giving notice from time to time, to them which are to ſucceed, the ſix dayes before they are to make their appearance at the appointed place. Alſo if ſeven or more of the Commiſſioners before named ſhall be preſent in this ſervice, three whereof or more to be Deputy-Lieutenants of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall and reſpective counties, the whole number ſhall have power to Vote, and the major part to rule the Vote.</p>
            <div type="instructions">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:132886:3"/>
               <head>Instructions for the Committee of the Aſſociated Counties.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IMprimis,</hi> That the ſaid firſt Committee ſo appointed as aforeſaid, and all other the ſaid Commiſſioners before named, are hereby ſtrictly required to make their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance according to the manner of the appointment by this preſent Ordinance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in theſe times of eminent danger, to uſe all diligence to promote the ſervice they are intruſted withall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That they have a ſpeciall care that all the Frontiers, and the Iſle of <hi>Ely</hi> be ſupplyed with fitting Forces to reſiſt all ſudden ſurpriſes or invaſions; &amp; ſhall from time to time ſend out Scouts to diſcover how, and in what manner, any enemy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procheth near to the Frontiers that thereby they may have, and give timely notice of any approching danger, &amp; this to be done at the generall charge of the Aſſociation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the ſaid Committee ſhall order and diſpoſe of all the Aſſociated Forces ſent to them by the ſaid Counties in ſuch ſort and manner as they ſhall think fit, and beſt for the ſafety of the ſaid Aſſociated Counties; And if at any time they ſhall find occaſion of more Forces fit to be raiſed by the Aſſociated Counties, they ſhall give notice thereof, to the Deputy-Lieutenants, that fitting ſupplies may be made thereof, and that every County may ſee their Forces paid.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That all Forces raiſed before this Ordinance in the Aſſociated Counties, ſhall be paid their Arreares if any be unpaid, by money raiſed out of the ſix Aſſociated Counties, and city of <hi>Norwich,</hi> according to their proportions.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the ſaid Committee ſhall take a ſpeciall care that an acomptant be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to Regiſter all the Warrants and directions of the ſaid Committee, and that they require the ſaid Acomptant or Regiſter to make and keep a perfect Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt how all moneys are paid in there by any of the Aſſociated Counties, &amp; how the ſame be iſſued out, &amp; ſhall give them ſuch reaſonable allowance for their pains.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That they have a ſpeciall care, that no ſtranger ſhall come in, or inhabit within the Town of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> or the Iſle of <hi>Ely,</hi> without the Approbation of the ſaid Committee, upon Certificate of his or their good affections to the King and Parliament; and alſo that they bring a Certificate under foure of the Deputy-Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants hands of the county from whence they come.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That all Souldiers that run away, ſhall be remanded back to the Colours, or ſent to the Goale; and all thoſe that harbour, are to be fined and impriſoned, they knowing them to be run-away, and to be further puniſhed, as my Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and the Deputy-Lieutenants of their reſpective counties, or any two of them ſhall think fit, the fine not exceeding five pounds every offence.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtration in the aforeſaid Counties reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, do preſently execute the Ordinances of Parliament for Sequeſtrations, or elſe to be certified by the ſaid Committee to the Houſes of Parliament, to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt for their neglect; And the ſaid Committee ſhall have power to put in execution all Ordinances of Parliament where there is any neglect.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That every Member of the Houſe of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, &amp; the Governours of <hi>Cambridge</hi> that are Inhabitants of the Six counties of <hi>Norfolk, Suffolk, Eſſex, Hertford, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingdon</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and of the city of <hi>Norwich,</hi> ſhall be of the ſaid Committee.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:132886:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Die Jovis</hi> 10. <hi>Augusti,</hi> 1643.</p>
            <p>ORdered by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the Aſſembly that are Reſiants of the Aſſociated counties, and now attending the Aſſembly, are hereby deſired to go down in to their ſeverall counties, to ſtirre up the people in thoſe ſeverall counties, to riſe for their defence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Die Jovis</hi> 10. <hi>Auguſti,</hi> 1643.</p>
            <p>ORdered by the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, That the Lord Generall the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> is hereby deſired, to grant a Commiſſion to the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> to be Sergeant Major Generall of all the Forces of the ſix Aſſociated counties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Die Jovis</hi> 10. <hi>Augusti,</hi> 1643.</p>
            <p>ORdered by the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, That the ſix Aſſociated counties ſhall forthwith raiſe a Body of ten thouſand Foot, and Dragoons, to withſtand the Enemy. And that four thouſand Foot, formerly Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to be raiſed in theſe ſix Aſſociated counties, or which are already raiſed, ſhall be accompted part of theſe ten thouſand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:132886:4"/>
            <head>An Ordinance of the Lords and Commons is Parliament, for explanation of a former Ordinance for ſequeſtration of Delinquents eſtates.</head>
            <p>FOr explanation and enlargement of an Ordinance lately made by the Lords and Commons in Parliament, for ſeizing and ſequeſtring the Eſtates both Reall and Perſonall of certain kinds of notorious Delinquents;</p>
            <p>Be it now Declared and Ordained by the ſaid Lords and Commons aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, That in the number of ſuch Delinquents and Papiſts, who ſhall come within the compaſſe of the ſaid former Ordinance, and to all intents and purpoſes to be proceeded againſt, as notorious Delinquents or Papiſts, expreſſely deſcribed in the ſaid Ordinance, ſhall be reckoned and accounted all ſuch as voluntarily abſenting themſelves from the uſuall places of their abodes, or dwellings, Trade, Offices, or Employments, and have gone, or ſhall go to any of the Kings Armies, or other forces raiſed without conſent of both houſes of Parl. and have there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, or ſhall there continue, and ſhall not within ten dayes after Seizure or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtration of their ſeverall goods or eſtates, or ſtay made of their Rents by force of the ſaid Ordinance, which ſaid Sequeſtratours are hereby required to do, ſhew ſufficient cauſe to be allowed by the Committee of the Countie, Citie, or Place in which the ſaid Seizure or Sequeſtration, or ſtay of Rents, is, or ſhall be made, of ſuch their abſence, going, and continuing in any of the ſaid Armies or Forces: And all ſuch as ſhall fraudulently imbezle, conceal, or convey away, all, or any part of their goods, money, or eſtate, without valuable conſideration, or not <hi>bonâ fide</hi> thereby preventing or avoiding the paiment of any taxes or Aſſeſſements laid upon them by any Ordinance of both Houſes of Parliament, or any diſtreſſe or ſeizure in caſe of <hi>non</hi>-paiment thereof; or that after any ſuch tax or aſſeſſement laid on them, convey themſelves away, or refuſe to be ſpoken with, whereby any tax or aſſeſſement laid upon them by Ordinance of both Houſes of Parliament cannot be executed upon them or their eſtates, according to the true meaning and purport thereof: or that wittingly or willingly conceal or harbour any goods or perſons of Delinquents, within this or the ſaid former Ordinance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or that have had any hand in the late horrid and deſperate Conſpiracie and Treaſon of <hi>Waller, Tompkins, Challenor</hi> and their Confederates, whether they be already, or hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall be convicted to be privie or conſenting thereunto (except ſuch as being not yet convicted ſhall diſcover and confeſſe all that they know thereof, within the time limited by both Houſes of Parliament, to ſuch perſon or perſons as are or ſhall be appointed to take ſuch diſcoveries and Confeſſions) or that ſhall ſue or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt any perſon or perſons who ſhall have yielded obedience or conformitie unto the Orders, Ordinances, or Commands of both houſes of Parliament, or have been, or ſhall be employed by authoritie of both the ſaid houſes, for, or by reaſon of any thing done, or to be done, in execution or performance thereof, or that have wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly harboured any Popiſh Prieſts or Jeſultes in their houſes or dwellings ſince the 29. of <hi>November</hi> 1642. or that ſhall hereafter ſo harbour any: And all and every perſon or perſons which at any time heretofore have been convicted of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh recuſancie, and ſo continue, or that have been or ſhall be thereof indicted, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132886:5"/>their Indictments removed by <hi>Certiorary,</hi> or being not removed ſhall not by appearance and Traverſe be legally diſcharged, before Seizure or Sequeſtration made of their goods or eſtates, or ſtay of their Rents, by force of this, or the ſaid former Ordinance, or that have been at Maſſe, at any time within one whole year before the 26. of <hi>March</hi> 1643. or ſhall hereafter be at Maſſe; or whoſe Children or Grand-children, or any of them living in houſe with them, or under their, or any of their Tuition and Government, ſhall be brought up in the Popiſh Religion: and all ſuch perſons as being of the age of 21. years, or above ſhall refuſe to take the Oath hereafter expreſſed; which Oath any two or more of the ſaid Committees for Sequeſtration, in every Countie, Citie, or place reſpectively, or any two Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Peace, or the Major, Bailiffs or other head-officer of any Citie or Town Corporate, ſhall have power to adminiſter to any ſuch perſon or perſons (The Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of which Oath followeth, <hi>in haec verba,</hi> viz.</p>
            <div type="oath">
               <head>The Oath.</head>
               <p>I A. B. <hi>Do abjure and renounce the Popes Supremacie and Authoritie over the Catholick Church in generall, and over my ſelf in particular; And I do believe that there is not any Tranſubſtantiation in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, or in the Elements of Bread and Wine after Conſecration thereof, by any perſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; And I do alſo believe, that there is not any Purgatorie; Or that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Hoaſt, Crucifixes, or Images, ought to be worſhipped, or that any worſhip is due unto any of them; And I alſo believe that Salvation cannot be Merited by Works, and all Doctrines in affirmation of the ſaid Points, I do abjure and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, without any Equivocation, Mentall-reſervation, or ſecret Evaſion what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, taking the words by me ſpoken, according to the common and uſuall meaning of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So help me God.)</p>
               <p>Shall forfeit as Papiſts within this and the ſaid former Ordinances, and Seizure and Sequeſtration of two third parts of all their goods and eſtates Reall and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall, and ſale of ſuch proportion of their goods ſo ſeized and Sequeſtred ſhall be made, and their Rents and eſtates diſpoſed of, in ſuch manner and proportion, and by ſuch perſons as by the ſaid Ordinance of Sequeſtrations is appointed for Papiſts.</p>
               <p>And for the better diſcoverie of ſuch Delinquents and Papiſts, in this, and the ſaid former Ordinance deſcribed, and of their eſtates; Be it further Ordained, by the ſaid Lords and Commons, That over and beſides the former power given by the ſaid Ordinance of Sequeſtration to the perſons truſted and employed in the ſaid ſervice, the ſaid Committees for Sequeſtrations, or any two or more of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectively, ſhall have power further hereby, to examine by Oath or otherwiſe, all and every perſon or perſons (other then the parties themſelves ſo declared to be Delinquents) that probably may be able to diſcover ſuch Delinquents and Papiſts, or that may be truſted with, or privie to the keeping or concealing of the goods or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:132886:5"/>eſtates of any ſuch delinquent or Papiſt, or that ſhall ow any thing to ſuch delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Papiſt, and ſuch as ſhall refuſe ſo to be examined, or to declare the whole truth therein, ſo farre as he ſhall be ſo required, ſhall be committed to ſafe cuſto die by the ſaid Committee, or any two or more of them, employed for their examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, till he or they ſhall conform him, her, or themſelves.</p>
               <p>And that ſuch perſon or perſons as ſhall firſt find out and diſcover to one or both Houſes of Parliament, or to any Committee authorized for this Service, or to any of their Agents or Officers, any ſuch moneys, goods, debts, or eſtates (if the ſame be imbezelled, cloyned, concealed, or conveyed away, as aforeſaid) ſhall do therein an acceptable ſervice to the Common-wealth, and ſhall have and receive for his pains therein 12. d. in every twentie ſhillings, ſo diſcovered after Seizure or ſale thereof made, and receit of the money ariſing thereupon, or out of the Rents or eſtate ſo diſcoverered, the ſame to be paid unto him by the reſpective Committees, or Treaſurers truſted with the moneys that ſhall be received upon the Sale, or Proceed thereof, without any further or other Warrant, and ſhall further receive ſuch other reward for his extraordinary ſervice therein, as by the ſaid LORDS and COMMONS ſhall be further appointed and Ordered: And for the more ſpeedie and effectuall Seizure, and obtaining poſſeſſion of all ſuch Debts, Goods, and Eſtates, as aforeſaid, diſcovered, or to be diſcovered.</p>
               <p>It is further Ordained, that over and beſides the Power given by the ſaid former Ordinance for Sequeſtration, the ſeverall and reſpective COMMITTEES, appointed for this Service, or any two, or more of them, ſhall hereby have Power to authorize their ſeverall Collectours, and Agents, employed herein, to break open all Locks, Bolts, Barres, Doores, or other ſtrength whatſoever, where any ſuch eſtates, moneys, or goods, are or ſhall be, upon probable grounds made appear to the ſaid Committees or any two of them, and by them allowed in writing under their hands, to be provided that ſome or one of the ſaid Committee, or the Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, or Conſtable, or ſome other known Officer of that countie or Place; and one other perſon or perſons of credit and truſt be preſent at the doing thereof; and it is further ordained, that an exact Inventorie, ſubſcribed by all their hands, be taken of all particulars whatſoever, which ſhall be ſeized bo virtue of theſe Ordinances: one part of the ſaid Inventorie in writing ſo ſubſcribed, delivered to the owner or owners of the ſaid money, goods, or eſtates, or other things ſo Inventoried, or to ſome perſon truſted with the keeping thereof. And that where any Rents, Debts, or eſtate pertaining to any Delinquent or Papiſt within this or the ſaid former Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance for ſequeſtration ſhall be found due, and the Debtour refuſeth or neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to pay the ſame, upon any pretenſe whatſoever, reaſonable time being given to provide it, after it become payable, and demand thereof made, the ſaid Committees, their Collectours or other Agents whom they ſhall authorize thereunto under their hands in writing, ſhall hereby have power to diſtrain, ſeize, carrie away, and ſell ſo much of the goods and eſtate of every ſuch perſon ſo refuſing or negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting as aforeſaid, as may fully ſatisfie the ſaid Rents or other Debts, together with all charges of ſeizure, removall, and ſale of goods for ſatisfaction of the ſaid Rents or Debts: And if any perſon or perſons ſhall ſtand out or forbear to make
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132886:6"/>payment of any ſummes of money which he or they ought to pay by virtue of this or any other Ordinance of both Houſes of Parliament whatſoever, made for the raiſing of moneys, untill a diſtreſſe be taken for the ſame; that then he or they ſo ſtanding out or forbearing, ſhall pay ſuch double charges for all ſuch ſeizures, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movall, and ſale of their goods, as the Committee or any two or more of them reſpectively ſhall allow or appoint; the ſame to be levied and taken out of the goods and eſtates of ſuch perſons ſo ſtanding out or forbearing, by ſuch as ſhall be employed to diſtrain for, and ſeize the principall ſumme. And if any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall undertake for the forth coming of any goods or eſtate at any time ſeized, by force of this or the ſaid former Ordinance, all and every the ſaid goods or eſtate ſhall be particularly Inventoried, and the Inventory thereof ſigned and ſubſcribed by three or more perſons of credit, and after given in to the Committee, under whom the perſons making the ſeizure ſhall be employed; and if it ſhall after hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that any of the ſaid goods or eſtate be imbeziled or wanting, or be denied or refuſed, or not delivered to the ſaid reſpective Committee, or to their Collectours, requiring the ſame by order of the ſaid Committee, or any two or more of them reſpectively, that then the ſaid Committee, or ſuch as they ſhall authorize thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſhall have power to ſeize, carry away and ſell ſo much of ſuch undetakers goods or perſonall eſtate, and profits of his Lands and Tenements, as may fully ſatisfie for the goods or eſtate ſo wanting, imbezilled, or not delivered; and alſo ſo much double charges for the ſeizure, carriage, and ſale of the ſaid undertakers goods or eſtate ſo to be ſeized and ſold, as the ſaid Committees, or any two or more of them ſhall allow.</p>
               <p>And for the better enabling of the ſaid ſeverall Committees, and their Agents, to make ſale of all ſuch goods and eſtates as are and ſhall be by them ſeized, and are appointed to be ſold by this or the ſaid former Ordinance,</p>
               <p>It is further declared and ordained, that after the apportioning and ſetting out of ſome neceſſary maintenance (if it be deſired) for the wives and children of ſuch Delinquents whoſe goods and eſtates are and ſhall be ſeized (which allowance or maintenance the ſaid ſeverall and reſpective Committees, or any two or more of them reſpectively, ſhall hereby have power to make, ſo, as they allow not the wife and children of one Delinquent above one fifth part of his goods and eſtate ſo ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) they ſhall authorize and require their Collectors and Agents to make ſale of the reſidue or remainder of the ſaid goods by the Candle for ready moneys to be paid at the delivery of the goods ſo ſold, within ten dayes after the ſeizure thereof, giving notice of the ſaid ſale in writing upon ſome poſt or walls in the moſt open and eminent places near the place of ſale two dayes before the ſaid ſale, due appraiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being firſt made thereof by two skilfull appraiſors; being men of ſome quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and known integrity, from time to time to be choſen with the advice of the Sollicitour for ſequeſtrations, by the Committee truſted with the ſeizure and ſale of the ſaid goods: which appraiſment ſhall be made in the preſence of ſome of the ſaid Committees, Sollicitour, or Treaſurer of the ſame County, City, or place reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, and not otherwiſe. And for the more ſpeedy diſpatch hereof, it is further ordained, that the Committee of Lords and Commons for ſequeſtrations fhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132886:6"/>no information againſt the particular Committee of any Countie, Citie, or place for ſequeſtrations in any cauſe of this kind, till the matter hath firſt been certified under the hands of two or more of the ſaid reſpective Committees by whoſe Agents and Miniſters the goods or eſtate of the Delinquent were ſeized: Or in caſe the ſaid Committees refuſe to certifie the ſpeciall matter, or that otherwiſe Certificate cannot be had. And be it ordained, that honeſt, able, and ſufficient Collectours be appointed in every Countie, Citie, and place for this ſervice, and their neglects or defaults be certified to the Houſes, or to the Committee of Lords and Commons for Sequeſtrations.</p>
               <p>And that all and every perſon and perſons, who ſhall be employed in this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or ſhall do any thing in purſuance of this or the ſaid former Ordinance for Sequeſtrations, ſhall therein have the protection of both houſes of Parliament for their Indemnitie, and be held and eſteemed as perſons doing an acceptable ſervice to the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>And it is further ordained, that every Collectour within every Countie, Citie and place reſpectively who ſhall receive any moneys in kind, or make ſale of any goods, ſhall deliver the moneys ſo received or raiſed by ſales, to the Committee for Sequeſtrations within the ſaid Countie, Citie, or place, where ſuch moneys ſhall be received, or to ſuch Treaſurer as they ſhall appoint, or other perſon authorized to receive the ſame within ſeven dayes next after the ſaid Collectours receit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, upon pain of forfeiture of twelve pence for every twentie ſhillings, received or levied by ſale as aforeſaid, and remaining in his or their hands, which Committee or Treaſurer, ſhall take order for the ſafe ſending of all, and every ſumme ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to the Treaſurer at Guild-Hall in <hi>London</hi> appointed for this purpoſe, Monethly, or more often, as they ſhall be thereunto required by the ſaid Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours at Guild-Hall, or by the ſaid Committee of Lords and Commons for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrations, or by the Committee of Lords and Commons for advance of moneys; and that the ſeverall Committees, Collectours, and Treaſurers reſpectively, ſhall have power to give acquittances and diſcharges for the ſeverall ſummes by them received, which ſhall be ſufficient diſcharges to the parties concerned in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half.</p>
               <p>And it is further ordained and declared, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hobſon,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bernardiſton,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hill,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Samuel Avery,</hi> Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> ſhall be and are hereby appointed, and authorized to be Treaſurers at Guild-Hall London, to receive all moneys raiſed and to be raiſed upon, or by virtue of this, or the ſaid former Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for Sequeſtrations, and ſhall make entries thereof in fair books to be provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for that purpoſe, as alſo of the names of the perſons, from whom, and the time when they receive the ſame, and of their disburſements and payments out; for which their pains and ſervice, they ſhall have three pence in every pound, which they ſhall ſo receive to be debated out of the ſaid ſummes received.</p>
               <p>And it is further ordained that no Treaſurers truſted with any part of the ſaid moneys, ſhall iſſue out any of the ſaid moneys by way of payment, loan, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, (except as in this Ordinance is appointed) otherwiſe then and in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as is directed by former Ordinance for iſſuing out of moneys; and for the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132886:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>more exact and perfect keeping of all accounts touching the premiſſes; it is yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordained, that every Collectour ſhall from time to time, make and keep a ſure and perfect Inventorie of all and every the moneys, goods, and eſtates by him ſeized, another of the ſale or other diſpoſall thereof; both of which ſhall be ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed under the hands of two or more perſons of credit that were preſent at the ſaid ſeizures or ſales, beſides his own, and that he make and ingroſſe a duplicate thereof in parchment, fairly written, one part whereof he ſhall leave with the particular Committee, under which he is employed; and the other part after examination thereof, he ſhall deliver to the Solicitour for that place, who ſhall tranſmit the ſame to the Committee of Lords and Commons for advance of money ſubſcribed by the ſaid Solicitour, and Collectour, and two of the ſaid particular Committee of the place from whence it is tranſmitted, all which accounts and duplicates ſhall be made and ſent up to <hi>London</hi> in ſuch manner and ſo often as the ſaid Committee of Lords and Commons for advance of money, ſhall from time to time order and appoint: Provided alwayes, and it be ordained, that it ſhall be lawfull for the reſpective Committees for Sequeſtrations, or any two or more of them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of ready money for the goods of the ſaid Delinquents or Papiſts, or any of them which ſhall or are to be ſeized according to the value thereof, in lieu and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the ſaid goods, and thereupon the ſeizure and Sequeſtration, as to the ſame, to be diſcharged.</p>
               <p>And be it ordained that if any perſon ſhall wittingly or willingly conceal and harbour any of the goods of any Delinquents within this or the ſaid former Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance (he knowing ſuch perſon to be a Delinquent) that then ſuch perſons ſhall forfeit treble the value thereof, to be levied upon his or their goods and eſtates, by the ſaid reſpective Committee or Sequeſtratours, or any two or more of them, or their agents, to the uſes appointed by the ſaid Ordinances for Delinquents Eſtates.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
